in any society
food is at the center of social life and
even cultural identity because imagine
japan without sushi italy without pizza
mexico without tacos
each country has its own unique food and
without it it wouldn't be the same
so what better way to get to know the
romans than to take a closer look at
their food
nowadays italian food is probably the
most well-known and appreciated food in
the entire world and it generally
revolves around two things pasta and
tomatoes
but forget about that because pasta as
we know it today was not known to the
ancient romans as with tomatoes and all
of these other products most of them
come from south america and only enter
the european kitchens a thousand years
after the romans
so what did the romans eat then if it
wasn't tomato sauce pasta and pizza
when we think of culinary habits
nowadays each nation has a staple cheap
carbohydrate filler mostly either rice
potatoes or pasta
as we said potatoes were not yet known
rice was rare and had to be imported
from india and the only ancient pasta we
know of is best described as some sort
of small round lasagna sheets
this does resemble modern day pasta but
it seems it was highly in common
something else had to make up the core
of the roman diet and that something was
called frumentum meaning cereals
either pure or made into bread but
before we dive into the world of roman
cereals a quick word for our sponsor
endl
much more so than in roman times
nowadays we live in an increasingly
distracting environment with all sorts
of impulses coming in all the time and
this affects us mentally and physically
endo is a non-profit app that helps
people deal with this by creating
personalized soothing soundscapes
these soundscapes adapt in real time to
personal inputs like location weather
and heart rate
listening to endl improves your
concentration boosts productivity
reduces stress levels and relieves brain
fatigue
these soundscapes give your mind and
body what it needs to achieve total
immersion in any task whether you need
to focus relax or sleep
specifically for falling asleep andal
just released a new soundscape made in
cooperation with james blake called wind
down
we mostly use the app to help us focus
when writing scripts
and it has proven to be real effective
for us
no surprise as the work of endo is
backed by neuroscience
so check it out now by clicking the
description in the link down below to
get a 7 day free trial
a telling way in which grain is shown to
be the cornerstone of the roman diet
were the three grain handouts in rome
installed already in the second century
bc in the time of the republic
hundreds of thousands of the poorer
citizens of rome received a monthly free
ration of grain amounting to some 35
kilos enough for a month of bread for
two persons
this was one of the first and for the
time most impactful forms of a social
safety net
it was a way to keep the population of
the capital fed and in that way help
combat hunger poverty corruption crime
and unrest in general
it was broadly accepted as essential for
the survival of rome and lasted until
the fall of the empire
in later times it was replaced by bread
giving us the phrase bread and games
but before that what did all these
people do with their grain
well one of the most common dishes in
ancient rome was a porridge called pools
the most traditional version amounts to
nothing more than ammer wheat boiled in
some salted water until soft and edible
to fasten the boiling process it'd be
smart to soak the grain overnight first
but even then the boiling takes roughly
an hour
so it's not exactly the fastest dish
it is easy to make though and nutritious
and cheap
from a price per calorie point of view
this is the absolute best poor man's
meal
on top of that it's highly versatile it
could be eaten warm or cold as breakfast
lunch or dinner as a side dish or a main
dish it really was the staple of the
roman diet especially for the poorer
romans
we can imagine poor people making this
in large quantities at a time to save on
firewood and eating the bets spread out
over multiple days
the only downside to this dish really is
the blend taste its entire need of some
flavor
no surprise there were many varieties of
which a handful of recipes survive
for example we know of one type of pools
that was made into a nicely balanced one
pot meal with onions beans and pork
added to it
another one was made with a base of
roasted barley then mixed with cumin
flaxseed and millet which was ground to
a fine powder before cooking it into a
thick sturdy porridge much like polenta
a sort of potato mesh like substance
made of ground corn flour still eaten
today in italy
and there was even a sweet one for
dessert with soft cheese and honey added
in and these are just some recipes that
survived after 2000 years
such types of grain porridge can be seen
as the substitutes of potatoes rice or
pasta
combined with the available ingredients
at the time there must have been an
endless variety of dishes with each
region and each family having their own
recipes and methods of preparation
but even then like nowadays you just
want something different now and then
was there something else to add to your
meal for some cheap calories
yes of course another option was to make
bread out of grain
bread provided some nice variation to
the grain porridges so bread was eaten a
lot
alongside meals at whatever moment of
the day
the most fascinating evidence for the
popularity of bread is a written
overview of eight days worth of shopping
uncovered on a wall in a house in the
ancient buried town of pompei
the list is a countdown of eight
consecutive days towards the ides the
middle of the month with a shopping list
for each of the days
it tells us this family's diet consisted
mainly of bread porridge cheese fruits
vegetables nuts and of course olives
olive oil and wine
interestingly enough bread is part of
all eight of the lists and consistently
put as the first item on the lists
you can say quite literally this
family's diet started with bread then
came the rest
they ate bread every day and bought it
fresh every day too
exceptions aside this was likely the
case for all the well-off families
being able to replace the cheaper poles
for bread more often
plautus a famous roman playwright
sometimes described characters in his
place as pulse eaters
this was meant in a condescending
derogatory way as to say these were
lowly simple people eating just a bland
mush
and when you think about it
porridge still kind of has an image of
being old-fashioned cheap and boring
certainly not something to serve your
guests
but also the poorer families who relied
on the free grain handouts would not be
solely reliant on porridge as they could
take a portion of their grain handout
and bring it to the baker so that he
could make it into bread for a small
price of course
or they could choose to buy the cheapest
bread because there were many types of
bread each with its own price
the shopping list alone mentioned no
less than three types of bread
just bread
coarse bread and bread for a slave
these clearly indicate different
qualities showing us that bread was
available for all layers of society
in general you know white bread was the
most beloved and most expensive
white bread was the most expensive
because it was made of the finest flour
in general the darker the bread the
coarser and cheaper
here you go lady one bread for you thank
you
thank you very much have a nice day
until next time
the most famous roman bread was the
so-called panis cuaratus
so-called because of four cuts or
impressions across the bread dividing it
into eight easily breakable pieces
this kind of bread is not famous because
of
the resemblance with pizza with the
different parts
but because we know exactly what it
looked like
not just because of its depictions on
wall paintings but more so because 80
such loaves have been found inside an
oven in pompeii carbonized and black but
still giving us this real-life tangible
ancient bread 2000 years later it's an
extremely rare and clear window into the
past
the abundance of depictions and mentions
of the bread suggests that this was the
most common bread available at least in
pompeii
next to the regular loaves there are all
sorts of specialist breads breads with a
specific purpose or characteristic
lenticulum for example was a flat and
round loaf tracta was more like a dry
cracker artologanus was a fatty cake
bread made with milk and lard
spoil stickers was a hurry bread
oyster bread to be eaten specifically
with oysters
or light and soft parthian bread
water bread light and full of holes like
a sponge excellent for dipping in wine
or olive oil sacrifice of breads for the
gods
big cannon a bread with nuts and honey
the list goes on and on
it is clear the romans cared for their
daily bread
and as much demand as there was so much
offer was there to meet it
bread could be bought the local bakery
itself
or it stands throughout the city for
example at the market or it stands next
to a temple selling sacrifice or bread
but for the real busy people bread could
even be delivered at home
the cheapest and most basic meal would
be to dip the bread in some wine it's a
good way to make all bread soft again
and make it easy to eat it quickly a
good way to have quick breakfast or an
easy meal on the road when there is no
fresh bread available
a similar meal is to dip your bread in
olive oil to add some extra flavor you
can add some salt garlic or green herbs
to the olive oil simple but tasty and
quite rich in calories and even
healthier than you might think because
olive oil contains lots of good fats and
antioxidants
studies have proven that eating olive
oil helps against the inflammations and
decreases the chance of heart diseases
strokes alzheimer and even cancer
then a step up in culinary complexity
would be to make a dipping sauce or
spread for bread
besides a pen the most important food
processing tool in any roman kitchen was
a mortarium
a heavy earthen bowl with its internal
surface embedded with coarse sand or
grit
like a mixing bowl and the grate in one
it was used to make all sorts of
delicacies of which the most well-known
is called muretum
a general term used for spreads and dips
usually based on the cheese combined
with ground and garlic and or herbs like
a modern day pesto or cheese spread
ideal for eating with bread and making
even the most boring bread delicious
and there are many cheeses to choose
from in antiquity as romans love cheese
cheeses were made from sheep goat and
cow's milk but the romans had a clear
preference for sheep and goat probably
because it's usually stronger in taste
the romans knew both fresh soft cheeses
like ricotta or cottage cheese as well
as aged heart cheeses and everything in
between
they even had a special smoked cheese
famously made in one specific
neighborhood in ancient rome
for many ordinary romans often times
cheese must have been the most tasteful
and expensive thing on the dinner table
but well worth it when considering the
golden combination it makes with red
wine bread and olive oil it turns an
ordinary meal into a real treat
then of course there are the things that
make our modern day dinner into dinner
vegetables and meats often cooked and
warm but the vegetables sometimes raw in
the form of salads
for the romans this was no different
lettuce rockets watercress the green
leaves of beets and many other smaller
plants were all eaten raw in the form of
salads
often vinegar and salt was added as a
dressing to the salad
the latin word for salt so is actually
where a word salad is derived from
as a more filling but healthy and cheap
side dish beans were perfect
most common and popular beans were
lentils chickpeas regular peas and broad
beans
with some roman culinary imagination
this could be made surprisingly tasty
such as a dish that is roughly
translated as fava beans a la vitellis
named after the gluttonous roman emperor
vitellius it's made of meshed broad
beans and egg yolks with an interesting
dressing of wine vinegar honey and
ginger
apart from beans the romans had many
other more green vegetables to choose
from as well some of the most popular
were broccoli cabbage leek asparagus and
celery to name just a few
but exotic items in itself weren't
uncommon either
because of the sheer size of the empire
and the relative safety of trade routes
economy blossomed like never before
resulting in more and more ingredients
entering the roman kitchens for example
black pepper produced in india has been
found in native homesteads all the way
in northwestern germania
products came from everywhere
olive oil and fish sauce from spain
wheat from north africa and egypt
cows from germania
cloves in nutmeg from india and beyond
next to importing new products the
romans also started the cultivation of
many products new to the local
population for example in germania there
were no plums apples peaches cherries
and walnuts until the romans arrived
the local population learned from the
romans how to grow these products
greatly increasing the variety of their
diet
finally
most expensive were fish and meat
when it comes to meat the romans had a
strong preference for pork
other livestock like chickens cows oxen
sheep and goats were held particularly
for the secondary products eggs traction
milk and wool
pigs don't offer any such secondary
products and were held purely for meat
purposes
their meat was therefore the most
expensive and maybe in part for that
reason the most craved
another likely reason for the liking of
pork is that it is the most fatty meat
and fat was considered nutritious and
therefore good the most popular ways to
eat meat was in the form of a stew or as
a sausage stuffed with minced meat and
mixed with spices and herbs
boiled meat was seen as less refined
then there's fish
fish came roughly in two varieties fresh
fish and preserved fish generally
speaking preserved salted fish would be
affordable for the common man as well
but fresh fish could cost anything
between a lot and a fortune especially
the rare and unusually big fish were
much sought after and being bought for
ridiculous prices
but they would not be for regular
day-to-day consumption though these fish
were clearly meant to impress important
guests
as food was one of the prime ways to
display your power in ancient rome so
the bigger rarer and more exotic the
better
it is only for this reason that we know
recipes of flamingos tongue sea urchins
camel's feet and giraffe meat
but this is the stuff of rome's ultimate
elite and hardly realistic even for them
this concludes our overview of the diet
of an ancient roman from poor to rich
thanks to the size and the vast trade
network of the empire
many products were available and cheap
it would take many centuries after the
roman empire before the common man had
access to such a varied diet again
well this concludes our video we hope
you enjoyed it and now it's time to do
the dishes
[Music]
you